מזל טוב, Mazel Tov, we are a good deal behind. Today's דף
daf should be י"ט, Yud Tet, but we pick up in the
middle of י"ח עמוד א' Yud Chet Amud Aleph by the two
dots,
three lines into the wider lines. קרא על פה לא יצא. Kara
al peh lo yatza. So if you read the מגילה Megillah orally,
meaning without reading it from a scroll, you do not fulfill your
obligation. And the גמרא Gemara says, מנלן, minalan, where do you know
this from? אמר רבא אתיא זכירה זכירה. Amar Rava atya zechira zechira.
It's the link of the word זכור זכור. zachor zachor. כתיב הכא
והימים האלה נזכרים, Ksiv hacha ve-hayamim ha-eleh nizkarim,
these days are remembered. And that we have known we have been
interpreting that to be about reading the מגילה. Megillah. וכתיב התם כתב
זאת זכרון בספר U-ksiv hatam ktov zot zikaron basefer by עמלק, Amalek,
and of course there's an obvious connecting here to the whole עמלק
Amalek and המן Haman and, you know, this is sort of the
culmination of that. And that's written in a book. מה להלן בספר
אף כאן בספר. Mah hallan basefer af kan basefer. So ממאי דהאי
זכירה קריאה היא? mimai de-hai zechira kria hi?
How do you know זכירה zechira means to, to like to read,
to recite? דילמא עיון בעלמא? Dilma iyun be-alma? Maybe it means readable?
Right, right? So נזכרים, nizkarim, so you read the book and you
remember.
I understood it was to read it by heart, to remember.
All right, good. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא סלקא דעתך. lo
salka daitach. That doesn't make sense. דתניא ברייתא זכור Di-tanya beraisa zachor
remember. So this is by עמלק. Amalek. יכול בלב, Yachol balev,
maybe just you know remember in your heart, in your mind. כשהוא
אומר לא תשכח, Keshehu omer lo tishkach, don't forget, הרי שכחת הלב
אמור. harei shichchas halev amur.
So that's referring to that it shouldn't be forgotten like forgetting of
the heart, meaning so you should actually mentally do remember, it's not
forgotten, it's remembered. הא מה אני מקיים זכור? Ha mah ani mikayem
zachor? So what's the power of the positive מצוה mitzvah of זכור
zachor to actively remember? What does it mean to actively remember? בפה,
Bpeh, orally. So that's the מצוה mitzvah of עמלק Amalek and here
too the מצוה mitzvah by again the link of עמלק Amalek to
the מגילה, Megillah, this זכור zachor is not just to keep it
in mind, it's to do an active remembrance which is, once we
have this idea of בספר, basefer, we have the idea that it's
an active reading. And as I mentioned, you know, and the Yosef
Yerushalmi talks about this a good deal in his book aptly named
זכור, Zachor,
which is about, you know, the whole Jewish concept first of all
of memory as opposed to history. Right, history is the fact that
happened, we really haven't had Jewish historians until like, you know, whatever,
last 150 years or so, but we've been excellent at memory, which
is creating a, you know, cultural and, you know, communal way of
of of of remembering certain things and of shaping history and shaping
our memory through—and this is the second point as opposed to memory
versus
history—through ritual acts. And ritual acts, you know, from all of the
רגלים, regalim, particularly יציאת מ- yitzias m- particularly פסח Pesach and the
הגדה Haggadah and all of these things, all of the מצוות למען
תזכור יום צאתך מארץ מצרים, mitzvos leman tizkor yom tzeischa me-eretz mitzrayim,
right, all of these things are about creating memory
and memory creating through, through ritual acts. So that's obviously a major
part of us as a Jewish people that, you know, the memory
of these events but the creation of the memory of those events
through, through ritual. Okay, so that's about how you know you're supposed
to read and read from a book. So now the גמרא Gemara
continues,
קרא תרגום לא יצא. Kara targum lo yatza. If you read it
in translation, Aramaic translation, you're not יצא. yotze. So the גמרא Gemara
says, היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא דכתיבא מקרא וקרי
ליה תרגום, Ileima de-chsiva mikra ve-karai lei targum, if it's written in
Hebrew and you're just and you're rather than reading the Hebrew you're
reading a translation, you know, the book in front of you is
in Hebrew, the scroll, but you're translating it. היינו על פה. Hainu
al peh. So it's an oral—so it's not from a book, it's
oral. לא צריכא, Lo tzericha, you need it for the case דכתיבא
תרגום וקרי ליה תרגום. de-chsiva targum ve-karai lei targum. It's written in
translation. So you have a scroll written in translation, reading it from
that scroll would not be good. So now, אבל קורין אותו, aval
korin oso, so that seems to say that the only acceptable thing
is a scroll in Hebrew. But then you get this next line
because you know you have to start with the scroll because you
have to read it from a scroll. So and by the way,
then it's not so clear, is the problem of reading from something
non-Hebrew that the reading has to be in Hebrew or that the
scroll has to be in Hebrew? Right, once we require a scroll,
so the insistence of Hebrew could be understood as an insistence in
the act of reading or could, you know, that somehow or it
could be insistence in what doesn't qualify as a legitimate scroll in
a different language. But so let's take a look at how that
gets played out in terms of this next issue of reading it
for foreigners in a foreign language. אבל קורין אותו ללועזים בלעז, Aval
korin oso le-loazim balaaz, you can read it for foreigners in a
foreign language. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמרת קרא בכל לשון לא
יצא. ve-amart kara be-chol lashon lo yatza. You just got through saying
that if you read it in another language you're not יצא. yotze.
So the גמרא Gemara says, רב ושמואל דאמרי תרוייהו, Rav u-Shmuel de-amri
tarvaihu, Rav and Shmuel both say, בלעז יווני. balaaz yevani. So they
want to situate the problem in the nature of the scroll. And
you'll remember that when we had a discussion earlier about that like,
you know, ספרים נכתבים בכל לשון sefarim nichtavin be-chol lashon and so
on, there's one opinion except
for— was a special exception. Right? So the position that you can't
write ספר תורה Sefer Torah in any other language except for Greek.
So רב ושמואל Rav and Shmuel are trying to solve the problem
that way and say the problem of reading the מגילה Megillah in
another language is the problem that the scroll isn't valid. So therefore
if you have a scroll in Greek, that might be the one
exception that another language is valid, then you could read it in
Greek. That would be the one allowance because then you would have
a valid scroll. So the גמרא Gemara says, well okay, so we're
not there yet, they're focusing on the scroll. So it says, בלעז
יווני. b'la'az Yevani. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא דכתיבא
אשורית וקרי לה יוונית? Ileima d'chativa Ashuris v'kari lei Yevanis? So the
גמרא, Gemara, I sort of jumped ahead to the end, the גמרא's
Gemara first figuring this out. If it's written in Assyriac, if it's
written in, you know, Hebrew script and you read it Greek, so
היינו על פה, hainu al peh, so you're just translating it. So
אמר רב אחא אמר רבי אלעזר שכתובה בלעז יוונית. Amar Rav Acha
amar Rabbi Elazar she'ktuva b'la'az Yevanis.
No,
it's written in Greek script. Okay good.
But let's say it's like transliterated.
Okay
we're not up to that yet. Okay, we're assuming so far we're
assuming exact parallel of the script and the language. Okay, ואמר רב
אחא אמר רבי אלעזר, v'amar Rav Acha amar Rabbi Elazar, מניין שקרא...
minayin she'kara... Now, before we get back to figuring this out, since
it's רב אחא אמר רבי אלעזר Rav Acha amar Rabbi Elazar we're
going to take a total digression and have a list of some
statements he made. ואמר רב אחא אמר רבי אלעזר... V'amar Rav Acha
amar Rabbi Elazar... Yes?
Question before we go into it. Yes, so what's going on? Are
they trying to piece together a tradition that past tradition, is one
trying to say well this is my case and here are the
particulars of it?
What is this?
What do you mean? Just in general the structure of when they
try to say well the case of the משנה's Mishnah talking about
X and then they sort of work it through, do they really
think that was the original meaning or are they just on themselves
creating a meaning that then will fit the existing text? Is that
your question?
That's a better question than my question.
What was your question?
Can we answer that question?
It depends case by case. What was your question? Okay fine. Anyways,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
here it seems like they really have to feel what the original
meaning of a text was because it wasn't two random texts that
are contradicting, the very same משנה Mishnah that says you don't read
in translation says you can read to foreigners in a foreign language.
So you would think that they are not just saying I can
make a way to reconcile, you think that there's a real meaning
that has to be uncovered here. But let's take a look as
the גמרא Gemara continues.
But what does uncovered mean? Does it mean I know the tradition?
Oh, is that your question? No, I don't think, it's very rare,
I mean but it's rare that somebody's saying I know this from
מסורה, mesorah, I mean that's רמב"ם's Rambam general point about תורה שבעל
פה Torah She'be'al Peh is that it's not like we have all
these traditions, you know, the traditions are small, it's like we're working
it out, we're figuring out what it might have been. So if
that's your question, then the general answer is that they're trying to
figure out what it meant, not that they're saying this is my
tradition what it meant. But, you know, it also is case by
case there. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואמר
רב אחא אמר רבי אלעזר, v'amar Rav Acha amar Rabbi Elazar, מניין
שקרא הקדוש ברוך הוא ליעקב אל? minayin she'kara Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Yaakov
El? How do we know that God called Jacob God, which is
pretty shocking? שנאמר: Shene'emar: ויקרא לו אל אלהי ישראל. vayikra lo El
Elohei Yisrael.
So this is about יעקב Yaakov making a מזבח mizbeach and it
says and he called it or him God the God of Israel.
So how do you read that? What, יעקב Yaakov called the מזבח
mizbeach God? That would be funny too. ואי סלקא דעתך למזבח קרא
ליה יעקב אל, V'i salka daitchach l'mizbeach kara lei Yaakov El, if
Jacob is calling the altar אל, El, which is itself very funny,
ויקרא לו יעקב מיבעי ליה, vayikra lo יעקב Yaakov miba'ei lei, it
should say then Jacob called it אל. El. So אלא, ella, as
although יעקב Yaakov was the subject of the previous verse, אלא ויקרא
לו ליעקב, ella vayikra lo l'Yaakov, so the verse previous verse mentioned
יעקב, Yaakov, then it's ויקרא vayikra God called him, called him יעקב,
Yaakov, אל. El. ומי קרא לו אל? U'mi kara lo El? Who
called Jacob אל? El? אלהי ישראל. Elohei Yisrael. So אלהי ישראל Elohei
Yisrael at the end of the verse is the subject, and אלהי
ישראל יקרא לו ליעקב אל. Elohei Yisrael yikra lo l'Yaakov El. Okay,
now this is the name of השם. Hashem.
All right, anyway, look, this raises huge questions, you know, I mean
but obviously, you know, I mean you know, we say in various
places like in the liturgy, you know, and you, I'm trying to
remember the verse, but anyway, you know, and you've called us by
your name, what's that thing we say in the
דאבנינג? davenen? ושמנו קראת בשמך? U'shmenu karata b'shimcha?
Yes, thank you. ושמנו קראת בשמך U'shmenu karata b'shimcha and so on,
now you could read ישראל, Yisrael, right, and אל El is part
of יעקב's Yaakov name, ישראל, Yisrael, but you know, this whole idea
of God, of you know, in kabbalistic literature, you know, the ten,
כנסת ישראל Kneses Yisrael is the tenth ספירה sefira of מלכות, Malchut,
you know, is sort of God's physical manifest... anyway, whatever. So there's
a lot here theologically, you know, and יעקב Yaakov is the face
on the כסא הכבוד. Kise Hakavod. Okay, so there's a lot here,
but we're going to have to bracket all that and move on.
Okay, back to the גמרא. Gemara. מיתיבי Meitivei says the גמרא, Gemara,
so now we've got that the משנה Mishnah means that you have
a scroll written in Greek and you can read it in Greek
and that's the one exception, which is a very
narrow interpretation. worst interpretation into the משנה. Mishnah. Let's go back to
the גמרא. Gemara. מיתיבי—or Meisvei where were we in the גמרא—let's Gemara
go back to our point. קרא גיפטית עברית עילמית מדית יוונית לא
יצא. Kara Giftis Ivris Elamis Madis Yevanis lo yatza. If you read
in any of these
languages—interesting it also mentions עברית, Ivris, which seems to
be—רש"י Rashi says לשון עבר הנהר, lashon ever hanahar, but it also
could just—that also might get to the fact of ancient Hebrew script.
So any of these scripts or any of these languages, you are
not יוצא. yotze. So how—so you see it says you're not יוצא
yotze with Greek? So how could רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel say
you're יוצא yotze with Greek? So the גמרא Gemara says: הא לא
דמיא אלא להא. Ha lo damya ella le-ha. No, the case that
it's good is like the
following ברייתא. Braisa. גיפטית לגיפטים עברית לעברים—so Giftis le-Giftim, Ivris le-Ivrim there
suggests that עברית Ivris is not just a different script but a
different language. עילמית לעילמים יוונית ליוונים יצא. Elamis le-Elamim, Yevanis le-Yevanim, yatza.
So you can read different languages for the people of that language,
which is הלא halla our משנה, Mishnah, ללעוזות בלעז. le-loazim belaz. So
then—so now it seems that our whole answer is: Okay, generally you're
not יוצא yotze if it's in translation, the scroll, but it works
if you're from that country. So אי הכי, i-hachi, רב Rav ושמואל
Shmuel אמאי מוקמי לה למתניתין בלעז יוונית? amai mokmi lei le-masnisin belaz
Yevanis? If the real exception hinges, which is again so funny it
took the גמרא Gemara so long to figure this out, if the
real exception hinges on the people of—that it's good for the people
of that language, then why did they have to make our משנה
Mishnah case of Greek? So לוקמה בכל לעז, lukmah be-chol laz, say
any—any language as long—and it's good for people of that country. So
אלא מתניתין כברייתא. ella masnisin ke-braisa. You're right. רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel got it wrong. Our משנה Mishnah is like the
ברייתא. Braisa. ללעוזות בלעז le-loazim belaz means—you for the people of that
language, of that nationality you can read it in their language. Again,
it's so bizarre why it took the גמרא Gemara so long to
figure that out. What else does ללעוזות בלעז le-loazim belaz mean, right?
So anyway, unless ללעוזות loazim is too generic of a statement. A
foreigner in a foreign language. So maybe it doesn't mean specifically that
country, that country's language. Although again, it seems like it's pretty much
פשט. pshat.
And with תרגום Targum
you're not יוצא yotze
with—okay, hold on. וכי מה דרב ושמואל Ve-chi mah de-Rav ve-Shmuel get
back to, דעלמא איתמר. de-alma ismar. So right, forget רב Rav and
שמואל. Shmuel. פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah is like the ברייתא.
Braisa. You can read it for a foreigner in the foreigner's language.
So when is רב Rav and שמואל's Shmuel point about Greek? A
different case, like a general case. רב ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav ve-Shmuel
de-amri duvaihu, because רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both say, לעז יווני
לכל כשר. laz Yevani le-chol kasher. That you can write scrolls, getting
back to the scroll, in Greek. Greek is an acceptable language for
writing scrolls, and like we had before a discussion of a ספר
תורה. sefer Torah. So the גמרא Gemara says: אמרי, Amri, I'm sorry,
I misread that. I'm getting—jump to the end. You can read in
Greek for anybody, not only for—for people from Greece, you can read—you
can read a יוונית Yevanis מגילה Megillah for any person. So the
גמרא Gemara says: הא קתני יוונית ליוונים? Ha katani Yevanis le-Yevanim? But
what do you mean? The ברייתא Braisa said you can only read
in Greek for Greeks. So the גמרא Gemara says: אין, In, ליוונים
אין לכולי עלמא לא? le-Yevanim in, le-chulei alma lo? Only for Greeks,
not for other people? So אינהו, inhu, they say, דאמר כרבן שמעון
בן גמליאל, de-amar ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, דתנן במתניתין de-tnan be-masnisin רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר אף ספרים לא התירו שיכתבו אלא יוונית. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer af sefarim lo hitiru she-yikasvu ella Yevanis. That you can only
write Torah scrolls in Greek, so they felt that Greek was an
alternative to Hebrew, so the same way you can read to anyone
in Hebrew, they felt you can read to anyone in Greek. So
you're right, the פשט pshat in our משנה Mishnah is if it's
a foreign language it can only be read for that country, for
those foreigners. Okay. However, if you want Greek—the same way Hebrew you
can read anyone, even if you don't really understand Hebrew can be
יוצא yotze by listening to Hebrew, anybody can also be יוצא yotze
by listening to Greek. And that's by רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel that says Greek by a תורה Torah is an
alternative—is the one thing that serves as an alternative to Hebrew, and
the same would be by the מגילה. Megillah. So ולימא הלכה כרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל? ve-leima halachah ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? So just say
we פוסקן pasken like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
So no, אי אמרי i amri הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, halachah
ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have said:
הני מילי hani mili שאר ספרים, she'ar sefarim, that's by other things
like a ספר תורה. sefer Torah. אבל Aval מגילה Megillah דכתיב בה
ככתבם, de-ksiv bah ke-chsavam, by מגילה Megillah it says as the way
it's written, and as we know, the גמרא Gemara says before that
even if a ספר תורה sefer Torah can be written in multiple
languages, מזוזות, mezuzos, תפילין, tefillin, and מגילה Megillah have to only be
written in Hebrew. And מגילה Megillah based on ככתבם, ke-chsavam, אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe Greek isn't good. קא משמע לן Kamashma lan that
it is. Okay, so where are we? We're to—the point here of
רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, which is—again, this is this bizarre issue
of the status of Greek which I'm not going to revisit because
we've done it a while ago, but they basically say the same
way you're יוצא yotze a מגילה—anybody Megillah can be יוצא yotze a
מגילה Megillah in Hebrew, even if you don't understand the language, you're
just listening, and that's enough, and we'll get to discuss that in
a minute, anybody can also be יוצא yotze hearing a מגילה Megillah
in Greek because Greek serves as some type of rough alternative to
Hebrew like we see of an earlier position of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Okay, now again, that might have been
about the—I just want to sort of make us think, that might
have been about the nature of the legitimacy of the scroll, the
scroll's kosher in another language. Here it's also the act of reading
in a language you don't understand, the same way that's good in
Hebrew, רב Rav ושמואל Shmuel says it's good in Greek. We don't
really פוסקן pasken that way, but anyway, that's the Greek thing. The
more relevant point for our משנה Mishnah understanding it is is that
a scroll written in a foreign language isn't good for a normal
person. normal person, but for somebody that is of that nationality or
from that, from that, is a natural speaker, a native speaker of
that language, it is good, which is saying two things. Number one,
the scroll constitutes a sufficient כשר kosher מגילה Megillah scroll, at least
from the perspective of the מצוה mitzvah object, a מגילה Megillah scroll
written in another language is a כשר kosher scroll, and that the
act of reading in a foreign language is also the act of
the מצוה. mitzvah. But all of that in the condition that this
person is actually of that language. Now, it's a little bit bizarre,
you know, where do you normally have this idea that, you know,
well, the מצוה mitzvah done this way is פסול pasul unless this
is like your nationality or whatever and then it's כשר. kosher. I
mean sometimes you get,
sometimes you get you have to use this hand unless you're a
lefty use that hand, I'm not sure that's exactly the same. Sometimes
by ברכת כהנים birkas kohanim you get this idea that if you
pronounce the words wrong, I mean if you, you know, if you,
if you have let's say a way of pronouncing certain vowels or
whatever, you wouldn't be able to say ברכת כהנים birkas kohanim unless
you're in a country where everybody pronounces, you know, their letters and
their vowels that way. But again, that's a little different than this,
which is really saying the entire scroll is different, the entire act
of reading is different. You know, to some degree though, it does
reflect the embracing of diversity, if you want to frame it that
way, of the מגילה, Megillah, of the idea of those that read
on the 14th, those that read on the 15th, those that read
on the 11th, 12th, 13th, a variation of practice. And you have
the idea which does also seem to be reflecting on the one
hand, we say ככתבה kichsavah means it has to be written exactly
the way it is in Hebrew. Of course, in the מגילה, Megillah,
what's, what's the context of ככתבה? kichsavah? For everybody! For all! ככתבם
וכלשונם! kichsavm v'chilshonam! It's exactly! לכושתיים ככתבם ולעברים ככתבם. Lakustis lakustim, la'ivri
la'ivrim.
Everybody gets the letter in their language and in their, you know,
and their script and in their language. So here we are really,
it's funny that until now ככתבה kichsavah has been used to limit
and say Hebrew, the way the מגילה Megillah that we're reading from
I guess is written, but really what it means is to embrace
a wide degree, a wide range of languages. Okay. So but that's
being sent to various people of various countries, get it tailored in
their script and their language, and that's being reflected here. If this
is your language, then you can have the מגילה Megillah written in,
מגילה? Megillah?
Yeah, מגילה Megillah in, for somebody that, yeah, I mean, right.
You're writing ספר תורה Sefer Torah but then you're writing, you know,
אחשורוש Achashverosh or whatever, yeah,
yeah, we really, yeah, you would. It'd be funny to actually hire
a scribe to write a מגילה Megillah בקלף be-klaf or whatever, but
you could, yeah, you could. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Now the question becomes for the middle range of people, about people
that are native speakers of a particular language but also understand Hebrew,
but don't understand it as well as they, you know, as they
understand their native language. Can they still be יוצא yotzei with it
written in their native language or is it only for people that
really don't understand Hebrew? You know, where exactly is the, is the
tipping point? But if somebody is, is fluent, you know, fully understands
the Hebrew then from again, I'd have to double check, but if
I remember you would not be יוצא yotzei in the native language,
English is for people that do not really understand Hebrew.
It's a second בדיעבד bediavad essentially.
Or it's, yeah, בדיעבד, bediavad, or when this is not a, you,
you know, I'm not sure if, yeah, I mean I'm not sure
if I'd frame it בדיעבד, bediavad, but it's only this idea that
we tailor it for particular people is when the, the Hebrew is
not accessible. Yes.
Missing from this is any discussion of the tradition of having a
תורגמן torgeman to translate.
Yeah, but a תורגמן torgeman is after the reading in the Hebrew.
So you could, you know, so when they read the ספר תורה
Sefer Torah they read it from the original and then they had
the תורגמן, torgeman, right? So, by the way Michael, and that might
be getting back to your question about the תורגמן, torgeman, right? Why
does it say you can't read it in translation? It's because normally
the תורגמן, torgeman, because why not? Everybody was speaking Aramaic! That's the
reason they had things with, you know, תורגמן, torgeman, because the, the
native language of the Jews in Babylon and even the Jews in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was Aramaic, right? That was the vernacular. But
this might be exactly this scenario where, okay, they sort of understood
the Hebrew, you know, and once you somewhat understand the Hebrew then
you don't have this option of reading it in the other language.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, do
you, are you יוצא yotzei if you hear it in Hebrew?
What? If you hear the Torah,
yeah, even, even
if you have no idea what it means you're יוצא. yotzei. That's,
can we draw some sort of
conclusion that it's more important to understand the story of Esther than
the, than the,
because you can hear it in another language even though you would
be יוצא yotzei hearing it in Hebrew? But it doesn't tell us
which is preferable. This by the way is a big question about
דאוונען. davening. You're יוצא yotzei דאוונען davening in another language. So let's
say you, let's say you, you know, you understand another language better,
is it better to read in the Hebrew and not really understand
what you're saying, or is it better to say it in another
language and understand what you're saying? So it's an interesting מחלוקת machlokes
in the פוסקים poskim about that, right? Which gets in a little
bit of the question, gets a little bit into the question about
ritual versus like, you know, the substance, the intent around the דאוונען.
davening. Is it better to really, you know, connect to the words
or is it better to follow the same ritual that everybody is
following? So anyway, so this would be, you know, a similar point,
right? So let's take a look. It's not clear which is preferable.
Yeah, this גמרא Gemara doesn't appear interested at all in like an
official translation or the quality of the
translation as opposed to if it's in Hebrew, of course,
exactly.
And that's going to be a question also, right? I mean, what
that's a question in general when we say you're יוצא שמע yotzei
Shma in other languages and so on, well how do you know
you're translating it precisely, you know? So apparently the גמרא Gemara says
you do the best you can. I guess maybe that's another reason
to prefer the Greek because then we have the official Septuagint translation.
I'm serious, you know, there's a real Septuagint tradition there. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says קרא ולו שמע שייש יצא, Kara v'lo shama
sheyesh yetza, that's the next line, right? So if you're a foreigner
and you hear it in the Hebrew, even if you don't know
what the language means, you're יוצא. yotzei. Which is preferable, again, is
not clear. Actually, the פשט pshat language of the משנה Mishnah is
that the foreign language is preferable. Right, קורים לו לועזות בלעז Korim
lo loazos bilaaz sounds like that's
לכתחילה, lechatchila, ולו שמע שייש יצא v'lo shama sheyesh yetza sounds like
that's בדיעבד. bedieved. But if you heard it in the Hebrew, you're
יוצא. yotzei. So it actually sounds like it's preferable to hear it
in the native language. What? It's not clear, but that's what it
sounds like. So the גמרא Gemara says והא לא ידעי מאי קאמרי?
V'ha lo yadai mai kaamri? How could you be יוצא yotzei in
Hebrew? You have no idea what's being said. So מידי דהוה אנשי,
midai d'hava anashei, לא אנשי, lo anashei, אנשים. anashim. Just like it's
by women and עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz and like, you know, the
the the laity, the people of the, the hoi polloi. So, what?
They don't they don't understand the Hebrew and they're יוצא. yotzei. So,
okay, makes sense, but doesn't but still doesn't explain why. So, מתקיף
לה רבינא, matkif lah Ravina, אטו אנן. atu anan. So רבינא Ravina
sort of, it's funny it says מתקיף לה matkif lah because he's
really coming, he's really מתקיף matkif on the question, not on the
answer. And he's sort of responding rhetorically to the question. Ah, you're
asking how
do we know, how do they know what it means? What, you
think we know what it means?
אטו אנן החשתרנים בני הרמכים מי ידעינן? Atu anan ha'achashteranim bnei haramachim
mi yadeinan? Who knows what this phrase means? החשתרנים בני הרמכים. Ha'achashteranim
bnei haramachim. אלא, Ella, so we also don't know what it means.
מצות קריאה ופרסומי ניסא. Mitzvas kriya u'pirsumei nisa. There's a מצוה mitzvah
to read it and it leads to a you know, a publicizing,
thank you, of the miracle. הכא נמי מצות קריאה ופרסומי ניסא. Hacha
nami mitzvas kriya u'pirsumei nisa. Here too, you read it, it publicizes
the miracle even if you don't know what it means. Now, it's
a little funny the phrase פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa because you if
you just said מצות קריאה, mitzvas kriya, הכא נמי מצות קריאה, hacha
nami mitzvas kriya, means you do the ritual act even if you
don't exactly know what the words mean. פרסומי ניסא Pirsumei nisa you
would think means in order to get the פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa
you have to understand what's being said. And it's one thing if
you don't understand a phrase in the context we pretty much know
what it means even if we don't know exactly what those words
mean, you know, it's another thing not to understand the whole thing.
But what he seems to be saying is that's the somehow the
public nature of that act and the general sense, we all sort
of know what the story is even if we don't know even
if we don't even know what the words mean, you know, that's
enough. There's not an idea of precise understanding. It's not like let's
say the question of, you know, let's say I don't know שמע
Shma where it's about קבלת עול מלכות שמים. kabbalas ol malchus shamayim.
See this is why I think he says פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa.
Like if I was talking about שמע Shma and I could say
it means to accept the yoke of heaven, how could you accept
the yoke of heaven if you're saying the words and have no
idea what they mean? But if the idea is to make a
big deal about the miracle, so the whole getting together and hearing
it read and having at least you know just some general sense,
you know you could also say people will be talking about it,
you know, it's the פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa can say yes there's
a larger point than just the act of reading but that larger
point doesn't have to mean specific understanding of exactly what the story
is. Yes.
You used the phrase publicizing the miracle. So are we talking just
the miracle to the Jews or to everyone?
Right, so that's in general a question, goes back to חנוכה Chanukah
when we say that you have to light it when people are
walking around the street still and רש"י Rashi says that the people
that are would be walking around, רש"י Rashi says are non-Jews. So,
but here in general we mean amongst the Jews, you know. If
you take a look רש"י Rashi says in פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa
about ten lines from the bottom אף על פי שאין יודעים מה
ששומעים שואלים את השומעים ואומרים מה היא הקריאה הזו ואיך הנסים מודיעים
להם. af al pi she'ein yod'im mah sheshom'im sho'alim es hashom'im v'omrim
mah hi hakriah hazo v'eich hanissim modiyim lahem. So there's, you know,
people get together and they talk and they shmooze what?
I like hearing it in the translation.
Right.
So but it is interesting, right, because the ritual act of the
reading is not the per se understanding of the story. So so
you know for רש"י Rashi but but it creates the experience of
פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, especially when it's done בציבור. b'tzibbur. What?
It just has a public involvement like on חנוכה Chanukah there's no
reading of anything. Right, like they tried to kill us, let's go
to shul.
There you go. I think that's a good comparison. So it's not
about Now the question is what would you say about a לועז
loaz that heard it בלעז bilaaz in private, not בציבור, b'tzibbur, right?
Does the פרסומי ניסא pirsumei nisa here have to be that it's
a public type of a of a thing? So would this also
work even even if even in private is not so clear. Okay,
so let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. קרא סירוגין
יצא. Kara seirugin yetza. If you read it with pauses, with breaks,
you're יוצא. yotzei. So now here's a גמרא Gemara that we've read
before in
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. The Rabbinic students didn’t know what the word
סירוגין seirugin meant. So שמעו לאמתא דבי רבי, shamu l'amta d'vei Rabbi,
they heard the maidservant in
רבי Rabbi’s house דאמרה להו לרבנן, d'amrah lehu l'Rabbanan, she said to
the rabbis דהוו פיסקי פיסקי d'havo piskei piskei that they would be
coming in with like breaks,
like you know, one group and then followed by another group, not
all at the same
time לבי רבי, l'vei Rabbi, they enter into רבי Rabbi’s house. עד
מתי אתם נכנסים סירוגין סירוגין, ad matay atem nichnasin seirugin seirugin, how
long is it going to be that you’re going to be entering,
you know, with chopped up breaks, breaks? So they understood, oh סירוגין.
seirugin. Now I understand what the משנה Mishnah means. לא הוו ידעי
רבנן, lo havu yad'ei Rabbanan, now the rabbis also didn’t know מאי
חלוגלוגות, mai haluglogot, what are חלוגלוגות, haluglogot, which is some type of
a vegetable which comes up in a number of
משניות. mishnayot. שמעו לאמתא דבי רבי, shamu l'amta d'vei Rabbi, they heard
the maidservant in רבי Rabbi’s house דאמרה ליה לההוא גברא, d'amrah leih
l'hahu gavra, she said to a certain person דהוה מפזר פרפחיני
d'hava
mefazer parpachini that he was sort of a scattering פרפחיני, parpachini, which
is some type of a vegetable.
עד מתי אתה
מפזר חלוגלוגיך, ad matay ata mefazer haluglogekha, until how long are you
going to be scattering your חלוגלוג? haluglog? So now they knew, oh
that’s the חלוגלוג haluglog in the משנה. Mishnah. I don’t know, what
does English say it is? Parsley. Parsley. Now we know.
לא הוו ידעי רבנן, lo havu yad'ei Rabbanan, the rabbis didn’t know
some phrases in the משנה, Mishnah, they also didn’t know some Hebrew
words: סלסלה ותרוממך, salsela u'teromemeka, you will be מסלסל mesalsel it and
it will lift you up. So שמעו לאמתא דבי רבי, shamu l'amta
d'vei Rabbi, they heard the maidservant in רבי Rabbi’s house דאמרה לההוא
גברא, d'amrah l'hahu gavra, she said to a certain man דהוה מהפך
במניא d'hava mehapech b'manya that he was sort of running his fingers
through his hair, he was always like tussling his hair. אמרה ליה,
amrah leih, she said to him עד מתי אתה מסלסל בשערך, ad
matay ata mesalsel b'sa'arekha, how long are you going to be like
running, you know, what would be the good for for that? Tussling.
Tussling. What would you call when he like he plays with his
hair and he runs his fingers through his hair?
Use him as a...
what?
Tussling? Run your fingers through your hair. What?
Delve into and turn over?
Oh, delve into and turn over is the verse, because they read
the verse about תורה. Torah. Right. What? Curling? Anyway, you know, you
run your fingers through it, anyway, you get into it, you delve
into it, right, and then the תורה Torah will lift you up.
Now it’s interesting, right, why is it that the, by the way,
notice the אמתא דבי רבי amta d'vei Rabbi is consistently speaking, at
least in the version of the story, in Hebrew, right? It’s an
Aramaic narrative but then when it quotes her it has her speak
in Hebrew and all these words are Hebrew, either משנה Mishnaic or
Biblical Hebrew, but they’re rarer Hebrew words. And again remember that the
vernacular was Aramaic, so could be though coming from רבי Rabbi’s house,
you know,
which a higher sort of like, you know, a more cultured learning
environment, academic and, well whatever, learning environment, could be that she was
just familiar with, you know, with more obscure Hebrew words. That Hebrew
was more of the sort of spoken or scholarly language that was
present in רבי Rabbi’s house.
If she was a...
oh there you go. They were in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay
but anyway.
More seriously, is this to be juxtaposed with the prior statement disparaging
women?
Oh,
that’s interesting. He said we just had that statement about women don’t
even know, and not only disparaging, disparaging women as not knowing the
Hebrew. Oh, that’s brilliant. Right, so we just got done talking about
women not knowing Hebrew and now here אמתא דבי רבי amta d'vei
Rabbi knows all the Hebrew that the, very nice excellent point. Okay,
excellent.
Head of the world in the morning.
Yeah, absolutely, absolutely.
Okay, that’s totally on target. Okay. I mean I was just thinking
that it echoes the idea that we don’t know what some phrases
mean, like החסר ואין רממים, hahaser ve'ein ramamim, but I think the
issue about here the woman knows what these phrases means is like
great. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. לא הוו
ידעי רבנן מאי השלך על ה' יהבך, lo havu yad'ei Rabbanan mai
hashlech al Hashem yehavcha,
they didn’t know what it meant when it said cast onto God
your יהב. yehav. So אמר רבה בר בר חנה, amar Rabbah Bar
Bar Chana, so now we’re leaving רבי Rabbi’s maidservant and we’re going
to other cases where they didn’t know what words meant. So רבה
בר בר חנה Rabbah Bar Bar Chana said זימנא חדא הוה אזלינא
בהדי ההוא טייא, zimna chada hava azlina behadi hahu Taya, one time
I was going together with this Arab, דקא דיינא טונא, d'ka daina
tuna, I was carrying a burden, ואמר לי, v'amar li, and he
said to me שקול יהבך ושדי אגמלאי, sh'kol yehavcha u'shadi agmalay, take
your burden and throw it onto my camel, and the word he
used for burden was יהבך, yehavcha, so cast your burden onto God.
Okay. לא הוו ידעי רבנן, lo havu yad'ei Rabbanan, the rabbis didn’t
know מאי וטאטאתיה במטאטא השמד, mai v'tatatiah b'matateh hashmed,
I will be מטאטא metateh it in the מטאטא metateh of the
שמד, shmad, so it means I will sweep it out with the
broom of destruction. So שמעו לאמתא דבי רבי, shamu l'amta d'vei Rabbi,
now back to רבי Rabbi’s household, they heard the maidservant of רבי
Rabbi’s household דהות אמרה לחברתה, d'havat amrah l'chavertah, she said to her
friend שקולי טטיתא וטטי ביתא, sh'kuli tatita ve'tati beisa, take your broom
and sweep out your house. So clearly it meant a broom and
to sweep. תנו רבנן, tanu Rabbanan, back to the discussion of מגילה.
Megillah. קרא סירוגין יצא, kara seirugin yatza, if you read it with
breaks you’re יצא. yotzei. סירוסין, serusin, if you read it backwards לא
יצא, lo yatza, you’re not יצא, yotzei, or you know, out of
order. רב מונא אמר משום רבי יהודה, Rav Mona amar mishum Rabbi
Yehuda, אף בסירוגין, af b'seirugin, even when it comes to סירוגין seirugin
אם שהה כדי לגמור... im shahah k'dei ligmor... חוזר לראש. chozer lerosh.
If you took the amount of time it takes, if the pause
you had was a big enough pause and break that you could
have read the whole מגילה, Megillah, I could have read a whole
מגילה Megillah right in the pause, then then you're not then you
have to go back to the beginning. Then you can't have a
sense of continuity. So אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef הלכה כרב
מונא. halacha k'Rav Mona. And רב יוסף Rav Yosef said we rule
like that. If it's too big of a pause, you're not יוצא.
yotza. שאמר משום רבי יהודה. she'amar mishum Rabbi Yehuda. אמר ליה אביי
לרב יוסף. Amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef. אביי Abaye said to רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, okay, how big of a pause are we talking
about? כדי לגמור כולה מהיכא דקאי לסופה? kedei ligmor kullah meheicha dekai
lesofah?
Long enough to finish to read to the end from where you're
up to to the end and that type of a pause would
be a break? או דילמא, o dilma, or do we say מרישא
לסופה, mereisha lesofah, a pause big enough to read the whole מגילה
Megillah from beginning to end? אמר ליה, Amar lei, מרישא לסופה. mereisha
lesofah. Now you have to say it means the whole מגילה Megillah
from beginning to end. דאם כן נתת דבריך לשיעורין. de'im ken natata
devarecha l'shiurin. A very important phrase in the גמרא. Gemara. Otherwise, you
would have given your statement to measurement. Now, not measurement as what
we always do, we try to quantify, but to measurements, meaning to
a range of measurement. You can't say this is the amount of
a pause that's a break, and then that size of the pause
changes every single time because where you're up to determines the size
of the pause. There has to be one fixed size, or else,
you know, you can't have a good type of a legal system
with so much variation. So therefore it has to be a fixed
amount. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב אבא
אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב הלכה כרב מונא. Amar Rav
Abba amar Rav Yirmeya bar Abba amar Rav halacha k'Rav Mona. So
again we have a statement in the name of רב Rav that
we rule like רב מונא. Rav Mona. Too big of a pause
breaks it up. ושמואל אמר אין הלכה כרב מונא. U'Shmuel amar ein
halacha k'Rav Mona. And שמואל Shmuel says we don't rule like him.
בסורא מתנו הכי. Besura masnu hachi. That's how they taught in סורא.
Sura. רב Rav says we rule like it and שמואל Shmuel says
we don't. בפומבדיתא מתנו הכי. Bepumbedisa masnu hachi. In פומבדיתא Pumbedisa they
say the following: אמר רב כהנא אמר רב הלכה כרב מונא. Amar
Rav Kahana amar Rav halacha k'Rav Mona. That רב כהנא Rav Kahana
says in the name of רב Rav we rule like רב מונא.
Rav Mona. ושמואל אמר אין הלכה כרב מונא. U'Shmuel amar ein halacha
k'Rav Mona. שמואל Shmuel says no. So there's very little difference. רב
Rav says we rule like it, שמואל Shmuel says we don't. The
only difference is who said it in the name of רב. Rav.
Was it רב אבא אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא Rav Abba amar
Rav Yirmeya bar Abba or was it just אמר רב כהנא? amar
Rav Kahana? But basically we have רב Rav saying we rule like
it, שמואל Shmuel saying we don't rule like it. ושמואל אמר אין
הלכה כרב מונא. U'Shmuel amar ein halacha k'Rav Mona. Now we get
רב ביבי מתני איפכא. Rav Bibi masni ipcha. רב ביבי Rav Bibi
reverses it. רב אמר אין הלכה כרב מונא ושמואל אמר הלכה כרב
מונא. Rav amar ein halacha k'Rav Mona u'Shmuel amar halacha k'Rav Mona.
Okay. So רב Rav said we don't rule like him and שמואל
Shmuel says we do rule like him. אמר רב יוסף נקוט דרב
ביבי בידך. Amar Rav Yosef nekote deRav Bibi beyadcha. Take רב ביבי's
Rav Bibi's tradition in your hand, that רב Rav says we reject
it and שמואל Shmuel says no, we rule that way. דשמואל הוא
דחייש ליחידאה. DeShmuel hu dechaish leyachida'ah. We know in general שמואל Shmuel
is concerned with דעת יחיד da'as yachid like, you know, individual opinions
to be safe and to be מחמיר machmir like them. דתנן, Detnan,
because we taught in the משנה Mishna in a completely different context:
שומרת יבם שקידש אחיו את אחותה. Shomeres yavam shekiddesh achiv es achosah.
You have a woman, you have somebody, את אחותה, es achosah, you
have, okay, look at that, somebody even erased the whiteboard. Okay,
so you basically have these three brothers, I know only two, but
let's make it three. Okay, you've got these three brothers, and he's
the oldest one. We'll call him ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי.
Levi. Okay, then you've got these two sisters,
רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. Okay,
and רחל Rachel was married to לוי. Levi.
לוי Levi
died. Okay, so now you've got רחל Rachel here over at the
corner. Okay,
so now you've got רחל, Rachel, and רחל, Rachel, לאה Leah wasn't
married yet. Okay, so רחל Rachel is שומרת יבם. shomeres yavam. It
means that ראובן Reuven or שמעון Shimon has to do either יבום
yibum or חליצה. chalitzah. I hope you're excited about this because this
is what's going to be occurring a lot within this מסכתא masechta
in a few months. Anyway, now the general practice is that ראובן
Reuven here, the older brother, is supposed to be the one that
first gets to decide like if he's going to do יבום yibum
or חליצה chalitzah or what. Okay? Now,
but שמעון Shimon in theory could also do יבום yibum except it's
supposed to go to ראובן. Reuven. While we're sort of waiting for
ראובן Reuven to decide what he's going to do, שמעון Shimon comes
along and he does קידושין kiddushin to לאה. Leah. Okay? Got the
scenario? Now, what's going to happen if ראובן Reuven does יבום yibum
to רחל? Rachel? If ראובן Reuven does יבום yibum to רחל, Rachel,
then he is married
to, wait a minute, now I'm confused.
Hold on one second.
Let me, let me just read רש״י Rashi again one minute.
Nice. So the point is like this. So forget what he's going
to do. The point is like this: because רחל Rachel in theory
is also somebody that he, you know, he has an obligation of
יבום yibum to, it precedes... is with ראובן, Reuven, but the, it's
possible for him to be יבום yibum with רחל. Rachel. And the
five idea that either of them might be able to do יבום,
yibum, right, is called זיקה. zika. זיקה zika basically means like a
connection. Okay, and that idea זיקה, zika, that connection that they basically
can have sex with her and then she'll become whoever one has
sex with her the wife, so there's like some type of a
pre-existing continuation of the marriage that he had with לוי Levi that
creates this connection that can be actualized when they do יבום, yibum,
so this idea of זיקה zika is seen as like a quasi-קידושין,
kiddushin, like a quasi-marriage that can be actualized if they choose to
do יבום. yibum. So the fact that he went ahead and did
קידושין kiddushin with לאה Leah is a bit of a problem because
he did קידושין kiddushin with לאה Leah when he had a זיקה
zika to רחל. Rachel. Okay, and that's what's the issue. And it's
like marrying two sisters. If he really were married to רחל, Rachel,
right, he couldn't have done קידושין, kiddushin, but he's not really married
to רחל, Rachel, he's got a זיקה, zika, but it's problematic. What
makes it less problematic is that ראובן Reuven comes first. So since
the real obligation devolves on ראובן, Reuven, his זיקה zika might be
a little immaterial because it's really his responsibility. So how do we
look at this, that he's married to לאה Leah and he has
a זיקה zika to רחל, Rachel, but he's really only second in
line? Okay, was that complicated enough? So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: שומרת יבם שקידש אחיו את אחותה.
shomeres yavam she-kiddesh achiv es achosa. So the brother married the sister,
okay? So משום רבי יהודה בן בתירה אמרו, mishum Rabbi Yehuda ben
Beteira amru, in the name of רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira they say, אומרים לו המתן, omrim lo hamten, you say
to שמעון Shimon wait before doing נשואין nisuim to לאה, Leah, עד
שיעשה אחיך הגדול מעשה, ad she-ya'aseh achicha hagadol ma'aseh,
until ראובן Reuven does what he needs to do. Until he either
does יבום yibum or חליצה. chalitza. If he does יבום yibum or
חליצה, chalitza, then he will free you from your זיקה. zika. Once
ראובן Reuven does whatever, whether it's יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitza, this
whole relationship goes off. So don't consummate your marriage with לאה Leah
until you're free from the זיקה zika that you have to, until
you're free from the זיקה zika because
ראובן Reuven will do what he needs to do.
More or less clear to the board? Yes, somewhat? Okay, so that's
the position. The other argument is שמעון Shimon doesn't have to worry
about it, it's all ראובן Reuven's responsibility and שמעון Shimon can go
ahead and do what he wants to do. But רבי יהודה בן
בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira here says no, you wait until שמעון
Shimon is totally freed from the זיקה zika and then ראובן Reuven
goes ahead and acts as he and until ראובן Reuven acts. Now
the relevance of this is אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יהודה בן בתירה,
amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira, and שמואל Shmuel says we
פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira. So
it's quite bizarre, like this is one case we had to find
where שמואל Shmuel says we פסקן pasken like a דעת יחיד, da'as
yachid, as דעת יחיד da'as yachid in all of ש"ס, Shas, שמואל
Shmuel is חושש choshesh for דעת יחיד. da'as yachid. But anyway, the
גמרא Gemara sees this as somehow indicative that sometimes there'll be an
opinion which we, everybody there's a consensus we really don't פסקן pasken
like, and שמואל Shmuel still wants to be concerned about it. And
therefore here too, that
the idea that שמואל Shmuel is the one that's חושש choshesh for
the size of the break, even though presumably the consensus is that
a break is not a problem in the מגילה Megillah no matter
how big it is, but we have a version that שמואל Shmuel
says no we have to be concerned, it makes sense that it's
שמואל Shmuel that's חושש choshesh for making a break rather than רב
Rav because שמואל Shmuel tends to be חושש choshesh with דעת יחיד.
da'as yachid. That's all very nice. Now how do we פסקן? pasken?
Now that we know that שמואל Shmuel says that, does that mean
we פסקן pasken like שמואל Shmuel or does it mean we פסקן
pasken like רב? Rav? So תוספות Tosafot says, okay good, שמואל Shmuel
is the one that's חושש choshesh for the דעת יחיד, da'as yachid,
but we know in a debate between רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel
we פסקן pasken like רב. Rav. So we are not חושש choshesh
for it, so now we're back to the idea that it doesn't
matter how big the break is and you're יוצא yotza even with
a very large break. Yes.
Even the strange opinion of רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben
Beteira isn't all that strange because he still permits קידושין, kiddushin, just
doesn't permit נשואין. nisuim.
Right. Well, question is he already did the קידושין, kiddushin, what if
he permitted it at the outset? Anyway I don't want to get
into it. Okay, תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Anyway there's the idea that
a big break is a problem, then there's a question is who
is חושש choshesh for it and then how do we פסקן. pasken.
General assumption is that we פסקן pasken that it's not an issue.
תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: השמיט בה הסופר אותיות או פסוקים, hishmit bah
hasofer osiyos o pesukim, let's say the מגילה Megillah scroll, later we'll
talk about what happens if you didn't read the whole scroll, but
now we're talking about the actual scroll itself is missing some words
or letters, at what stage does it stop being a כשרה kosher
scroll? Okay, so השמיט בה סופר אותיות או פסוקים, hishmit bah sofer
osiyos o pesukim, the סופר sofer left off some letters or verses,
so וקראן הקורא כמתורגמן המתרגם, v'karan hakoreh k'meturgeman hametargem, and the reader
read it like a מתורגמן meturgeman would translate, meaning he sort of
filled in the blanks. So he read it but the words weren't
in front of him, he just filled in the blanks. יצא, yatza,
he fulfilled his obligation. So that's telling you two things. It's telling
you number one if a scroll is missing some words or letters
it could still be a כשרה kosher scroll, how much we don't
know, and number two even though you have to read it from
a scroll, if you read some parts not from the scroll you
can also be יוצא. yatza. Okay, which is by the way an
important principle because here you are you're listening to the מגילה Megillah
and you have to be יוצא, yatza, שומע כעונה, shomea k'oneh, and
you have to hear every word, and then the בעל קורא, ba'al
koreh, you were distracted, your kid was talking to you or whatever
and you missed a few words. What do you do now? So
that's why a lot of people want to come with their מגילה
Megillah in front of them, so now I can go back and
I can read those words from the מגילה. Megillah. But guess what?
You can even read those words not from the מגילה. Megillah. The
same way the בעל קורא ba'al korei can read a few words
that aren't written down, so both the מגילה Megillah remains כשרה kosher
and the reading is כשרה. kosher. Not every word has to be
written from the מגילה. Megillah. If you missed a פסוק pasuk and
you missed some words, you can also just say them straight from
your printed מגילה Megillah and you're also... it's also fine. Now what's
the limit to that we're going to see? So let's take a
look.
Correct. Yes, and we're going to see at what stage will the
מגילה Megillah be פסולה. psulah. But certainly a few words, a few
פסוקים psukim is not a problem.
Okay. Correct. Right. The text has an independent existence whether it's written
or not.
Right. You mean because you can fill in the words...
the words, they exist out there and you say
them.
Right. But again, but mostly it has to be written from the
script. I'm saying a few words, a few פסוקים, psukim, right? The
basis or the גמרא Gemara says it has to be מתוך הספר.
mitchoch hasefer. You have to read it from the מגילה Megillah scroll.
But we allow some... not 100%. Parts of it don't... you know,
90%. We'll see what the percentage is, but it's not... the whole
thing can't exist independently. Basically it's from the scroll. So let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this. The גמרא Gemara says
מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you on this: היו אותיות מטושטשות או מקורעות
hayu otiyot mitushtashot o mekuro'ot if the letters were, like you know,
smudged or broken,
אם רשומן ניכר כשרה im rshuman nikar keshera if the mark of
them, meaning you can still certainly see the shadow of them there,
so it's still the right shape, it's כשרה. keshera. ואם לאו פסולה
ve'im lav psula if not it's פסולה. psula. So you see even
some letters are problems. לא קשיא הא בכולה הא במקצתה. lo kashya
ha bekula ha bmiktsata.
So now the גמרא Gemara says it's a difference of basically all
or part. Now, again, presumably it means that as long as it's
only... not all, but one would say רוב, rov, as long as
it's only up to 49 percent of the מגילה Megillah could basically
be missing words and missing letters, and it's still considered a כשרה
keshera מגילה, Megillah, even only 51 percent of it is written. Now
there is also another question about maybe something that's considered a whole
ענין, inyan, a whole section maybe can't be missing. Okay? But percentage-wise
it might be enough that you just have 51 percent of it
there and maybe certain whole sections can't be missing, and then that's
considered a good scroll and it's considered a good reading. Okay? So
that actually is the הלכה. halacha. The
גמרא Gemara continues: תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: השמיט בה הקורא פסוק אחד,
hishmit bah hakorei pasuk echad, so if let's say the person who
is reading it skips a פסוק, pasuk, לא יאמר אקרא את כולה
ואחר כך אקרא אותו פסוק lo yomar ekra et kula ve'achar kach
ekra oto pasuk I'm just going to continue reading and then at
the end I'll go back and read the פסוק pasuk I skipped.
That would be an example of reading it backwards. אלא קורא מאותו
פסוק ואילך. ela korei me'oto pasuk ve'eilach. You have to go back
to that verse and read from that verse point on. נכנס לבית
הכנסת ומצא ציבור שקראו חציה, nichnas l'veit haknesset umatsa tsibur shekar'u chatsyah,
which can easily happen, you come to שול shul and you missed
the first ten minutes and they're already on the second פרק. perek.
So לא יאמר, lo yomar, the obvious thing to say is: אקרא
חציה עם הציבור ואחר כך אקרא חציה. ekra chatsyah im hatsibur ve'achar
kach ekra chatsyah. I'll listen to the rest with the ציבור tsibur
and then I'll go back and I'll read the first פרק. perek.
I missed the first פרק. perek. No, I'm sorry, that's reading it
out of order. קורא
אותה מתחילתה ועד סופה. korei otah mitchilatah ve'ad sofah. You have to
read it from the beginning to the end. Okay. I'll just take
out just one second just to read you this הלכה halacha because
I know this sounds bizarre about this issue about how much of
the מגילה Megillah doesn't have to be present, just so you actually
hear because again, not only is it very relevant in terms of
the issue like I just told you that like if you miss
a פסוק pasuk you can read it by yourself, but also just
because yeah, I mean a lot of people have מגילות Megillot that
are actually not totally... you know, that have some missing letters or
whatever. So hold on one second, let me just find
you here... תרצ... Taf Reish Tzadi...
ah, what just happened?
Okay, here's the הלכה: halacha: וצריך
שתהיה
כתובה כולה לפניו לכתחילה v'tsarich shetehei ktuvah kulo lefanav lechatchilah
it all has to be in the scroll, אבל בדיעבד אם השמיט
הסופר באמצע תיבה אפילו עד חציה וקראו הקורא על פה יצא. aval
b'diavad im hishmit hasofer b'emtsa teiva afilu ad chatsyah vekara'o hakorei al
peh yatza.
So even up to maybe up to and not including 50 percent
of it is missing you're יוצא. yotze. הגה: Hagah: דהוא הדין, dehu
hadin, the רמ"א Rama says: אבל השמיט תחילה או סופה אפילו מיעוטה
לא יצא aval hishmit techilah o sofah afilu mi'utah lo yatza if
the very beginning is missing or the very end, even a little,
לא יצא. lo yatza. דאפילו באמצע דוקא שלא השמיט ענין שלם d'afilu
b'emtsa davka shelo hishmit inyan shalem
even in the middle it can't be a whole section that's missing,
etc. So that 51 percent, you can have 51 percent but it
doesn't also just... but also each certain section has to be represented,
there has to be a... each section has to be represented. But
even so, okay, to say that that still is a כשרה keshera
מגילה Megillah and that's still a כשרה keshera קריאה kriyah is significant
and it's significant if you missed 20 פסוקים psukim and it's not
a whole section and it's not the very beginning, if you can
read very fast you can say it on your own and catch
up.
Okay, so you still have to read, saying the whole thing.
Saying the whole thing, you got right exactly.
מתנמנם יצא. Misnamnem yatza. If you're dozing off, you're יוצא, yotzei, but
if you're slumbering, you're not יוצא. yotzei. So I assume it's more
relevant. I want to say that the משנה Mishnah says if you're
reading it while you're sort of falling asleep. If you're hearing it
while you're מתנמנם, misnamnem, I think it's pretty clear that you would
not have heard everything. Okay, but maybe if you're reading it and,
you know, again, I don't know how you do either of them.
Some people, I think, can continue talking in their sleep, you know,
but okay. מתנמנם יצא, היכי דמי מתנמנם? Misnamnem yatza, heichi dami misnamnem?
What's the example? אמר רב אשי: נים ולא נים, תיר ולא תיר,
Amar Rav Ashi: nim velo nim, tair velo tair, asleep and not
asleep, awake and not awake, דקרו ליה ועני, dekary lei ve’ani, somebody
calls you, you'll respond, ולא ידע לאהדורי סברא, velo yada le’ahadurei sevara,
but you can't say anything of sense, דכי מדכרו ליה מדכר, dechi
madkery lei midkar, but if they remind you, you'll remember. So you
say like, duh, so huh, what, yeah, like, you know, where are
the car keys? Like, I don't know. Did you leave them here?
No, no. Did you? Oh, yeah, yeah, whatever. So that's like that
state. Okay, so all right. היה כותבה, דורשה, ומגיהה, אם כיון לבו
יצא. Haya kotevah, dorshah, umagiha, im kiven libo yatza. Now we get
to the classic discussion of כוונה. kavanah. There you are, you're copying
over one scroll from the next. As you're copying it over, you're
muttering the words, and maybe not even aware you're muttering the words.
If you have intent, and there's always a question what intent: intent
to read or intent to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה? mitzvah? But
minimally intent to read, then
you're
יוצא. yotzei. So היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the scenario? says the
גמרא. Gemara. אי דקא מסדר פסוקי פסוקי וכתב לה. Ei deka mesader
pesukei pesukei vechatev lah. So if you are basically, you know, arranging
each verse, writing down basically one verse at a time, כי כיון
לבו מאי הוי? ki kiven libo mai havei? Who cares that you're
having intent? על פה הוא! al peh hu! It's על פה al
peh because you're basically writing down a verse. So the verse that
you've written down here, you know, before you wrote it, wasn't written.
Like you said, ויהי בימי אחשורוש, vayehi bimei Achashverosh, and then you
wrote ויהי בימי אחשורוש. vayehi bimei Achashverosh. So when you said ויהי
בימי אחשורוש, vayehi bimei Achashverosh, you weren't reading from something written, right?
So you were, so the words that you were saying were before
the words were written. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואמר רבי חלבו,
ve’amar Rabbi Chelbo, says רבי חלבו, Rabbi Chelbo, oh, where am I?
Did I skip
a line? מאי הוי? על פה הוא, אלא דכתב פסוקא פסוקא וקרי
ליה. Mai havei? Al peh hu, ela dechatev pesuka pesuka vekary lei.
No, so here's what you did: first you wrote ויהי, vayehi, and
after you wrote the word ויהי, vayehi, you said the word ויהי.
vayehi. And then you wrote בימי, bimei, and after you wrote the
word בימי, bimei, you said the word בימי. bimei. So each word
after it was written was being read. Okay, and therefore it's מתוך
הכתב. mitoch haksav. One minute. ואמר רבי חלבו אמר רב חמא בר
גוריא אמר רב: הלכה כדברי אומר כולה. Ve’amar Rabbi Chelbo amar Rav
Chama bar Guria amar Rav: Halacha kedivrei omer kullah. You have to
read all of it. It's not enough, we're going to have opinions
later that maybe you can read from the middle. No, you have
to read the whole thing. But then, and here's what's relevant for
us, דאפילו מאן דאמר מאיש יהודי, de’afilu man de’amar me’ish Yehudi, even
if it's enough to read the מגילה Megillah starting at איש יהודי
ish Yehudi and not from ויהי בימי אחשורוש, vayehi bimei Achashverosh, צריכה
שתהא כתובה כולה, tzrichah shetehei ktuvah kullah, it all have to be
written. You might not have to read all of it, but to
be a כשר kosher מגילה Megillah it all has to be written.
Now we just discussed exactly a minute ago what does it mean
to be fully to be written, but nevertheless, right, you can't just
say ויהי, vayehi, write the one word and read it, and then
בימי bimei and write that word and read it. Because then when
you're reading, you're not reading מתוך הכתב. mitoch haksav. You're reading from
a written word, but you're not reading from a כשר kosher מגילה.
Megillah. Like, so you got the scenario? You can't be writing and
then reading the the thing that's just the the ink is still
fresh on, because what you have in front of you isn't a
כשר kosher מגילה. Megillah. So therefore you and so even if you
didn't have to read all of it, you have to read from
a full מגילה. Megillah. How much more so here. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אלא, ela, what's the scenario? דמנחא מגילה קמיה וקרי לה,
וקרי לה מינה פסוקא פסוקא וכתב לה. demanacha Megillah kameih vekary lah,
vekary lah minah pesuka pesuka vechatev lah. It's
you're copying over from an existing מגילה. Megillah. So you're writing your
מגילה, Megillah, you have an existing מגילה Megillah here, you're writing your
מגילה, Megillah, you're looking here, ויהי בימי אחשורוש, vayehi bimei Achashverosh, and
then you're writing ויהי בימי אחשורוש, vayehi bimei Achashverosh, and then you
look at the next פסוק pasuk and you write it. So when
you're looking at the מגילה Megillah that's your source, you're reading from
that מגילה, Megillah, even though the new מגילה Megillah that you're writing
is not yet fully written. Okay, so that's actually quite a reasonable
scenario. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
לימא מסייעא ליה, Leima mesaye’a lei, let me come to support you,
לרבה בר בר חנה, le-Rabbah bar bar Chana, this this understanding.
דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, De’amar Rabbah bar bar
Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, because no, no, I'm sorry, misread. Let's say
that this understanding supports רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah bar bar Chana,
because רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana says in the
name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אסור לכתוב אות אחת שלא מן
הכתב, assur lichtov os achas shelo min haksav, that you can't even
write one letter. He's talking about a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. If
you're writing a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, that you're not copying from
an existing copy, just one you have to everything by looking at
an existing copy and copying it over. So therefore, if that's true
by ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, maybe it's true by מגילה, Megillah, and
that would explain why the scenario here could take for granted that
you're reading from a pre-existing מגילה, Megillah, because that's how you have
to write it over. So the גמרא Gemara says no. The גמרא
Gemara says, one minute,
דילמא דאיסטרמי ליה איסטרמויי. dilma de’istrami lei istramuyei. No, maybe halachically you
can write it not from a מגילה, Megillah, but it happens to
be the case we're talking about is you're copying from a מגילה.
Megillah. It doesn't prove you need to copy from an existing מגילה,
Megillah, that might just be the case. Okay, so let's look at
that. גופא. Gufa. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, אסור לכתוב אות אחת שלא
מן הכתב. assur likhtov ot achat she-lo min ha-ktav. You can't, by
a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, write even one letter that you're not
copying over from an existing copy. Okay, you understand the purpose of
this, right? Obviously, if you want to work, now it's even if
you're copying from an existing copy, copyists make mistakes all the time.
But at least to limit the mistakes, you want to insist on
every single letter copying over and not doing even one thing not,
because that'll just increase mistakes. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this.
אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, מעשה ברבי
מאיר, ma'aseh be-Rabbi Meir, there was a story with Rabbi Meir. Rabbi
Meir was a סופר, sofer, שהלך לעבר שנה באסיא, she-halach le-aber shanah
be-Asya, he went to Asia in order to make a leap year.
ולא היה שם מגילה, ve-lo hayah sham Megillah, and they didn't have
a מגילה Megillah there. וכתבה מפיו, ve-khetavah mi-piv, and he wrote it
by heart, he wrote it out by heart, he knew the whole
מגילה Megillah by heart. וקראה, ve-kera'ah, and they read it. So you
see you can write at least a מגילה Megillah שלא מן הכתב.
she-lo min ha-ktav. So אמר רבי אבהו, amar Rabbi Abbahu, says Rabbi
Abbahu, שאני רבי מאיר דמיקים ביה ואפעפיך יישירו נגדך. shani Rabbi Meir
de-mikim beih ve-afapekha yashiru negdekha.
By Rabbi Meir, the verse that says that your eyelids will be
sort of straight in front of you basically means the whole thing
was like written out beforehand. Like he knew it completely perfectly. So
basically this idea that you have to copy from a script is
not a technical הלכה, halachah, it's just to ensure accuracy.
So at least this stage is what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
So Rabbi Meir, who absolutely knew it every single letter, he was
allowed to do this. So אמר ליה רמי בר חמא לרבי ירמיה
amar leih Rami bar Chama le-Rabbi Yirmiyah מדפתי, mi-Difti, מה ואפעפיך יישירו
נגדך? mai ve-afapekha yashiru negdekha? What does it mean, this verse, your
eyelids, it should be straight in front of you? So אמר לו,
amar lo, אלו דברי תורה דכתיב בהו, elu divrei Torah de-khtiv behu,
this is referring to the words of Torah because it says התעיף
עיניך בו ואיננו, hata'if eynekha bo ve-enennu, if you flood your eye
away from it, it disappears. ואפילו הכי, ve-afillu hachi, and even though
for most
people
they forget at least with the precision of
תורה Torah and words of תורה Torah and the exact writing, at
least like תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh it's about the ideas,
here it's about every single letter, but אפילו הכי, afillu hachi, even
so, מיושרין הן אצל רבי מאיר, meyusharin hen etzel Rabbi Meir, for
Rabbi Meir it's all very clear and laid out, he has it
perfectly. So he was able to write שלא מן הכתב. she-lo min
ha-ktav. Okay, so until now it's just a safeguard and not an
absolute technical requirement. רב חסדא אשכחיה לרב חננאל, Rav Chisda ashkcheih le-Rav
Chananel, so Rav Chisda found Rav Chananel, דהוה כתיב ספרים שלא מן
הכתב. de-hava kativ sefarim she-lo min ha-ktav. He was writing over ספרים,
sefarim, presumably
ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, not copying them over from an existing ספר.
sefer. אמר
ליה,
amar
leih, he said to him,
ראויה כל התורה כולה ליכתב על פיך, re'uyah kol ha-Torah kullah likatev
al pikha, you know what, you, Rav Chananel, the whole Torah could
be written on your mouth, and it's like על פה, al peh,
like you got it all, you know it all perfectly. In principle
I have no question that you know every single letter perfectly. אלא,
ella, but what are you going to do? כך אמרו חכמים, kach
amru chachamim, the sages said, אסור לכתוב אות אחת שלא מן הכתב.
assur likhtov ot achat she-lo min ha-ktav. So he's saying either A,
we don't make exceptions, or B, it's not just a safeguard, it's
actually a technical requirement that every letter has to be copied over.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מכדי אמר כל התורה כולה ראויה היא
שתיכתב על פיך, mikhdi amar kol ha-Torah kullah re'uyah hi she-tikatev al
pikha, מכלל דמיושרין אצלו. mikhlal de-meyusharin etzlo. So you see it's a
similar scenario to Rabbi Meir, that Rav Chananel had it exactly perfect.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והא רבי מאיר כתב? ve-ha Rabbi Meir
ktav? But okay, but by Rabbi Meir we allowed it. So
what's going on here? Says, שעת הדחק שאני. she'at ha-dechak shani.
No, by Rabbi Meir it said nobody had a מגילה. Megillah. So
if there's a real שעת הדחק, she'at ha-dechak, we'll make an exception.
So again what we seem to be saying is, it's not a
technical requirement, technically the מגילה Megillah will be כשרה, kesherah, it's a
safeguard, but even for the safeguard we won't make exceptions for people
who know it perfectly, because once you start making exceptions everybody thinks
they know it perfect, so we're not going to make exceptions, but
in the שעת הדחק she'at ha-dechak where they wouldn't have had a
מגילה Megillah to read, there they made an exception. Okay, now, אביי
שרא לדבי בר חבו, Abaye shara le-de-bei Bar Chavu, Abaye allowed the
house of Bar Chavu, let's just get to the end, ומיכתב תפילין
ומזוזות שלא מן הכתב, u-mikhtav Tefillin u-Mezuzot she-lo min ha-ktav, to write
תפילין Tefillin and מזוזות Mezuzot שלא מן הכתב. she-lo min ha-ktav. Now
that of all the things you would think maybe has the most
in terms of a technical requirement, not just a safeguard, I mean
that's like the most of the ritual objects of scrolls. So כמאן,
ke-man, who's that going like? כי האי תנא, ke-hai tanna, like the
following תנא. tanna. דתני רבי ירמיה אומר משום רבנו, de-tanya Rabbi Yirmiyah
omer mishum Rabbeinu, תפילין ומזוזות נכתבים שלא מן הכתב. Tefillin u-Mezuzot nikhtavim
she-lo min ha-ktav. So maybe the exact opposite, we would have thought
maybe it has the most technical requirement and this says no, דווקא
davka תפילין Tefillin and מזוזות Mezuzot can be written not from copying
over from a scroll. ואין צריכין שרטוט, ve-ein tzerikhin sirtut, and it
does not need the scoring, scoring all the lines, the indented lines.
Okay, and so והלכתא, ve-hilkhata, and the הלכה halachah is, תפילין אין
צריכין שרטוט, Tefillin ein tzerikhin sirtut, מזוזה צריכה שרטוט, Mezuzah tzerikhah sirtut,
תפילין Tefillin does not need the scoring, מזוזה Mezuzah does, that's a
separate discussion. אידי ואידי נכתב שלא מן הכתב, idi ve-idi nikhtav she-lo
min ha-ktav, and you can write תפילין Tefillin and מזוזות Mezuzot without
copying them over, just by memory. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, מיגרס גריסינהו?
migras gariseynhu? Why? Because everybody knows them. Now I would say everybody
knows them orally, doesn't mean you know exactly which word has the
extra יוד yud or doesn't have the extra
יוד, yud, the exact spelling. of every single word. So this is
quite surprising. A, the assumption that they're so well-known, but B, the
idea that even in what I would call the most ritual of
the scrolls, you know, that it's not, it doesn't exist as a
technical requirement. This idea of מן הכתב min ha-ksav is only a
safeguard against error and not actually a formal requirement that determines whether
it's כשר kosher or not.
I was just curious if these were ever read.